<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rdmo xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" created="2024-06-22T16:32:55.578587+02:00">
	<catalog dc:uri="https://rdmo.nfdi4chem.de/terms/questions/NFDI4Chem_Vorlage">
		<uri_prefix>https://rdmo.nfdi4chem.de/terms</uri_prefix>
		<key>NFDI4Chem_Vorlage</key>
		<dc:comment/>
		<order>45</order>
		<title lang="en">Discipline specific: NFDI4Chem_Template</title>
		<help lang="en">The present questionnaire is a checklist issued by the German Research Foundation (DFG),
enriched with chemistry-specific content and supplemented with necessary questions for
better understanding and completeness.</help>
		<title lang="de">Disziplinspezifisch: NFDI4Chem_Vorlage</title>
		<help lang="de">Der vorliegende Fragenkatalog ist die von der Deutschen Forschungsgemeinschaft (DFG) herausgegebene Checkliste, welche für ein besseres Verständnis mit chemie-spezifischen Inhalten angereichert und um notwendige Fragen ergänzt wurde.</help>
	</catalog>
	<section dc:uri="https://rdmo.nfdi4chem.de/terms/questions/NFDI4Chem_Vorlage/data_description">
		<uri_prefix>https://rdmo.nfdi4chem.de/terms</uri_prefix>
		<key>data_description</key>
		<path>NFDI4Chem_Vorlage/data_description</path>
		<dc:comment/>
		<catalog dc:uri="https://rdmo.nfdi4chem.de/terms/questions/NFDI4Chem_Vorlage"/>
		<order>0</order>
		<title lang="en">Data Description</title>
		<title lang="de">Datennutzung</title>
	</section>
	<questionset dc:uri="https://rdmo.nfdi4chem.de/terms/questions/NFDI4Chem_Vorlage/data_description/data_content">
		<uri_prefix>https://rdmo.nfdi4chem.de/terms</uri_prefix>
		<key>data_content</key>
		<path>NFDI4Chem_Vorlage/data_description/data_content</path>
		<dc:comment/>
		<attribute dc:uri="https://rdmorganiser.github.io/terms/domain/project/dataset/id"/>
		<section dc:uri="https://rdmo.nfdi4chem.de/terms/questions/NFDI4Chem_Vorlage/data_description"/>
		<questionset/>
		<is_collection>True</is_collection>
		<order>0</order>
		<title lang="en">Content data description</title>
		<help lang="en">The present questionnaire is a checklist issued by the German Research Foundation (DFG), enriched with chemistry-specific content and supplemented with necessary questions for better understanding and completeness. The DFG checklist must be submitted with your application and at the project's completion and is intended to assist you in structuring your data management. If you have any questions, please contact the central Research Data Management (RDM) team at your university or research institution, or reach out to NFDI4Chem at &lt;a href="mailto:helpdesk@nfdi4chem.de" target="_blank"&gt;helpdesk@nfdi4chem.de&lt;/a&gt;.
 
&lt;u&gt;The following questions&lt;/u&gt; are for describing chemical datasets generated and/or used in the project. The definition of what constitutes a dataset is an important conceptual decision that must be made individually for each institute or project. Choose a logical unit of your research data as a dataset, to which the same information regarding methodology, technology, accessibility, etc., applies. This can be, for example, a molecule, synthesis steps, the employed analysis method, similar simulation calculations, etc. 

Categorising data into datasets helps assess the value of the data in terms of potential reuse and subsequent archiving. Since all questions must be answered for each individual dataset, an overly granular structure is not practical. Some aspects of data handling can be generalised and documented through accompanying policies. The preferred approach to managing data is typically communicated at the beginning of a project, either verbally or in writing, and is conveyed to subsequent doctoral candidates during their onboarding. An example of such a policy can be found from the Daumann Group at: &lt;a href="https://www.bioac.hhu.de/bioinorganic-chemistry/team-1-1" target="_blank"&gt;https://www.bioac.hhu.de/bioinorganic-chemistry/team-1-1&lt;/a&gt;.

You can use this catalogue of questions as a text document for support or in the Research Data Management Organizer (RDMO) tool provided for data management plans. This offers you the opportunity to collaborate with project partners, colleagues, NFDI4Chem, .... 
RDMO also offers you the following advantages:
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;RDMO supports your data management over the entire life of the project.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;RDMO can compile all relevant planning data and data management tasks over the entire life cycle of the research data.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The catalogue can be used in German or English, depending on your preference.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Various DMP templates are offered.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;RDMO can automatically distribute tasks to project members.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;RDMO has an import/export function and offers various formats for download.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</help>
		<verbose_name lang="en"/>
		<verbose_name_plural lang="en"/>
		<title lang="de">Inhaltliche Datenbeschreibung</title>
		<help lang="de">Der vorliegende Fragenkatalog ist die von der Deutschen Forschungsgemeinschaft (DFG) herausgegebene Checkliste, welche für ein besseres Verständnis mit chemie-spezifischen Inhalten angereichert und um notwendige Fragen ergänzt wurde. Die DFG-Checkliste muss bei Antragstellung sowie bei Projektabschluss mit eingereicht werden und soll Ihnen helfen, Ihr Datenmanagement zu strukturieren. Bei Fragen wenden Sie sich bitte an das zentrale FDM-Team Ihrer Universität/Forschungseinrichtung oder an NFDI4Chem unter &lt;a href="mailto:helpdesk@nfdi4chem.de" target="_blank"&gt;helpdesk@nfdi4chem.de&lt;/a&gt;. 

&lt;u&gt;Die folgenden Fragen&lt;/u&gt; dienen der Beschreibung von chemischen Datensätzen, die im Projekt erzeugt und/oder verwendet werden. Die Definition dessen, was jeweils ein Datensatz ist, ist eine wichtige konzeptionelle Entscheidung, die für jedes Vorhaben bzw. Projekt individuell getroffen werden muss. Wählen Sie als Datensatz eine logische Einheit Ihrer Forschungsdaten, für die gleiche Angaben bezüglich Methodik, Technik, Zugänglichkeit, usw. gelten. Dieses kann z.B. ein Molekül, Syntheseschritte, die eingesetzte Analysemethode, gleiche Simulationsberechnungen, usw. sein. 

Die Einteilung in Datensätze hilft, den Wert der Daten hinsichtlich der potentiellen Nachnutzung und einer späteren Archivierung einschätzen zu können. Da alle Fragen für jeden einzelnen Datensatz beantwortet werden müssen, ist eine allzu feingranulare Struktur nicht sinnvoll.

Einiges lässt sich im Umgang mit Daten verallgemeinern und kann durch eine begleitende Policy abgebildet werden. Der gewünschte Umgang mit Daten wird in der Regel zu Beginn eines Projektes mündlich oder schriftlich kommuniziert und bei weiterem Onboarding späterer Doktoranden vermittelt. Ein Beispiel für eine Policy finden Sie von der Daumann Group unter: &lt;a href="https://www.bioac.hhu.de/bioinorganic-chemistry/team-1-1" target="_blank"&gt;https://www.bioac.hhu.de/bioinorganic-chemistry/team-1-1&lt;/a&gt;.

Sie können diesen Fragenkatalog als Textdokument zur Unterstützung benutzen oder in dem für Datenmanagementpläne bereitgestellten Tool Research Data Management Organiser (RDMO). Dieses bietet Ihnen die Möglichkeit der Zusammenarbeit mit ProjektpartnerInnen, KollegInnen, NFDI4Chem, usw. 
RDMO bietet Ihnen darüber hinaus noch die Vorteile:
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;RDMO unterstützt Ihr Datenmanagement über die gesamte Lebensdauer des Projekts.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;RDMO kann alle relevanten Planungsdaten und Datenmanagementaufgaben über den gesamten Lebenszyklus der Forschungsdaten zusammenstellen.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Der Katalog kann je nach Belieben in Deutsch oder Englisch verwendet werden.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Es werden verschiedene DMP-Templates angeboten.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;RDMO kann Aufgaben automatisch an Projektmitglieder verteilen.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;RDMO verfügt über eine Import/Export-Funktion und bietet verschiedene Formate zum Download an.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</help>
		<verbose_name lang="de"/>
		<verbose_name_plural lang="de"/>
		<conditions/>
	</questionset>
	<question dc:uri="https://rdmo.nfdi4chem.de/terms/questions/NFDI4Chem_Vorlage/data_description/data_content/ds_description">
		<uri_prefix>https://rdmo.nfdi4chem.de/terms</uri_prefix>
		<key>ds_description</key>
		<path>NFDI4Chem_Vorlage/data_description/data_content/ds_description</path>
		<dc:comment/>
		<attribute dc:uri="https://rdmorganiser.github.io/terms/domain/project/dataset/description"/>
		<questionset dc:uri="https://rdmo.nfdi4chem.de/terms/questions/NFDI4Chem_Vorlage/data_description/data_content"/>
		<is_collection>True</is_collection>
		<is_optional>False</is_optional>
		<order>0</order>
		<help lang="en"/>
		<text lang="en">What kind of dataset is it?</text>
		<default_text lang="en"/>
		<verbose_name lang="en"/>
		<verbose_name_plural lang="en"/>
		<help lang="de"/>
		<text lang="de">Um was für einen Datensatz handelt es sich?</text>
		<default_text lang="de"/>
		<verbose_name lang="de"/>
		<verbose_name_plural lang="de"/>
		<default_option/>
		<default_external_id/>
		<widget_type>checkbox</widget_type>
		<value_type>option</value_type>
		<maximum/>
		<minimum/>
		<step/>
		<unit/>
		<width>12</width>
		<optionsets>
			<optionset dc:uri="https://rdmo.nfdi4chem.de/terms/options/4chem_dataset_what"/>
		</optionsets>
		<conditions/>
	</question>
	<question dc:uri="https://rdmo.nfdi4chem.de/terms/questions/NFDI4Chem_Vorlage/data_description/data_content/ds_newData">
		<uri_prefix>https://rdmo.nfdi4chem.de/terms</uri_prefix>
		<key>ds_newData</key>
		<path>NFDI4Chem_Vorlage/data_description/data_content/ds_newData</path>
		<dc:comment/>
		<attribute dc:uri="https://rdmorganiser.github.io/terms/domain/project/dataset/creation_methods"/>
		<questionset dc:uri="https://rdmo.nfdi4chem.de/terms/questions/NFDI4Chem_Vorlage/data_description/data_content"/>
		<is_collection>True</is_collection>
		<is_optional>False</is_optional>
		<order>1</order>
		<help lang="en">Research data is typically generated in every research project. Here, you should
reflect upon and describe the ways in which you generate research data. The methods of
data generation may vary depending on your specific chemical subdiscipline. Consider the
methods and tools you use.</help>
		<text lang="en">How does your project generate new data?</text>
		<default_text lang="en"/>
		<verbose_name lang="en"/>
		<verbose_name_plural lang="en"/>
		<help lang="de">Forschungsdaten entstehen in der Regel in jedem Forschungsvorhaben. Hier sollen Sie reflektieren und beschreiben, auf welche Art und Weise Sie Forschungsdaten erzeugen. Die Erzeugung hängt dabei von Ihrer chemischen Subdisziplin ab. Denken Sie dabei auch an Methoden und Tools, die Sie verwenden.</help>
		<text lang="de">Auf welche Weise entstehen in Ihrem Projekt neue Daten?</text>
		<default_text lang="de"/>
		<verbose_name lang="de"/>
		<verbose_name_plural lang="de"/>
		<default_option/>
		<default_external_id/>
		<widget_type>checkbox</widget_type>
		<value_type>option</value_type>
		<maximum/>
		<minimum/>
		<step/>
		<unit/>
		<width/>
		<optionsets>
			<optionset dc:uri="https://rdmo.nfdi4chem.de/terms/options/NFDI_new_data"/>
		</optionsets>
		<conditions/>
	</question>
	<question dc:uri="https://rdmo.nfdi4chem.de/terms/questions/NFDI4Chem_Vorlage/data_description/data_content/ds_reuse">
		<uri_prefix>https://rdmo.nfdi4chem.de/terms</uri_prefix>
		<key>ds_reuse</key>
		<path>NFDI4Chem_Vorlage/data_description/data_content/ds_reuse</path>
		<dc:comment/>
		<attribute dc:uri="https://rdmorganiser.github.io/terms/domain/project/dataset/origin"/>
		<questionset dc:uri="https://rdmo.nfdi4chem.de/terms/questions/NFDI4Chem_Vorlage/data_description/data_content"/>
		<is_collection>True</is_collection>
		<is_optional>False</is_optional>
		<order>2</order>
		<help lang="en">In chemistry, existing data are often reused. The most commonly used data include
crystal structures and analytical results used for comparing newly generated data. Existing
data can also serve as the foundation for a new project or be used for specific parts of the
project. This is often the case with data generated within research groups. Check to see if
you can use any existing data for your project.

Possible databases:
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://icsd.fiz-karlsruhe.de/search/basic.xhtml;jsessionid=3E38CBFD6DABF1686D
0F84DBFDA12FED" target="_blank"&gt;Inorganic Crystal Structure Database&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://materialsproject.org/" target="_blank"&gt;Materials Project&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.chemotion-repository.net/welcome" target="_blank"&gt;chemotion Repository&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

Additionally, NFDI4Chem offers a &lt;a href="https://search.nfdi4chem.de/" target="_blank"&gt;Search Service&lt;/a&gt;  that allows
simultaneous searches across multiple chemistry-specific repositories.</help>
		<text lang="en">Is existing data reused?</text>
		<default_text lang="en"/>
		<verbose_name lang="en"/>
		<verbose_name_plural lang="en"/>
		<help lang="de">In der Chemie werden oft existierende Daten wiederverwendet. Zu den meist verwendeten Daten zählen Kristallstrukturen sowie Analyseergebnisse, die zum Vergleich der neu erzeugten Daten dienen. Existierende Daten können auch die Basis des neuen Projektes bilden oder auch nur für Teile des Projektes verwendet werden, dies ist bei Arbeitsgruppen-internen Daten häufig der Fall. Informieren Sie sich vor Ihrem Projekt, ob Sie bereits erzeugte Daten nutzen können. Mögliche Datenbanken sind beispielsweise:
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://icsd.fiz-karlsruhe.de/search/basic.xhtml;jsessionid=3E38CBFD6DABF1686D0F84DBFDA12FED" target="_blank"&gt;Inorganic Crystal Structure Database&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://materialsproject.org/" target="_blank"&gt;Materials Project&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.chemotion-repository.net/welcome" target="_blank"&gt;chemotion Repository&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
Außerdem bietet NFDI4Chem einen &lt;a href="https://search.nfdi4chem.de/" target="_blank"&gt;Search Service&lt;/a&gt; an, der es ermöglicht, gleichzeitig mehrere chemiespezifische Repositorien zu durchsuchen.</help>
		<text lang="de">Werden existierende Daten wiederverwendet?</text>
		<default_text lang="de"/>
		<verbose_name lang="de"/>
		<verbose_name_plural lang="de"/>
		<default_option/>
		<default_external_id/>
		<widget_type>checkbox</widget_type>
		<value_type>option</value_type>
		<maximum/>
		<minimum/>
		<step/>
		<unit/>
		<width/>
		<optionsets>
			<optionset dc:uri="https://rdmo.nfdi4chem.de/terms/options/NFDI_reuse_data"/>
		</optionsets>
		<conditions/>
	</question>
	<questionset dc:uri="https://rdmo.nfdi4chem.de/terms/questions/NFDI4Chem_Vorlage/data_description/technical_description">
		<uri_prefix>https://rdmo.nfdi4chem.de/terms</uri_prefix>
		<key>technical_description</key>
		<path>NFDI4Chem_Vorlage/data_description/technical_description</path>
		<dc:comment/>
		<attribute dc:uri="https://rdmorganiser.github.io/terms/domain/project/dataset/id"/>
		<section dc:uri="https://rdmo.nfdi4chem.de/terms/questions/NFDI4Chem_Vorlage/data_description"/>
		<questionset/>
		<is_collection>True</is_collection>
		<order>1</order>
		<title lang="en">Technical Data Description</title>
		<help lang="en"/>
		<verbose_name lang="en"/>
		<verbose_name_plural lang="en"/>
		<title lang="de">Technische Datenbeschreibung</title>
		<help lang="de"/>
		<verbose_name lang="de"/>
		<verbose_name_plural lang="de"/>
		<conditions/>
	</questionset>
	<question dc:uri="https://rdmo.nfdi4chem.de/terms/questions/NFDI4Chem_Vorlage/data_description/technical_description/ds_format">
		<uri_prefix>https://rdmo.nfdi4chem.de/terms</uri_prefix>
		<key>ds_format</key>
		<path>NFDI4Chem_Vorlage/data_description/technical_description/ds_format</path>
		<dc:comment/>
		<attribute dc:uri="https://rdmorganiser.github.io/terms/domain/project/dataset/format"/>
		<questionset dc:uri="https://rdmo.nfdi4chem.de/terms/questions/NFDI4Chem_Vorlage/data_description/technical_description"/>
		<is_collection>True</is_collection>
		<is_optional>False</is_optional>
		<order>0</order>
		<help lang="en">Different devices may produce various data formats, some of which may not be
compatible with each other. Additionally, some device manufacturers use proprietary data
formats. When choosing a data format, it is advisable to use standardised, non-proprietary
formats that are commonly used in chemistry. Raw data should also be retained in the
original file format if the file size allows.</help>
		<text lang="en">Which data types (in terms of data formats) arise in your project?</text>
		<default_text lang="en"/>
		<verbose_name lang="en"/>
		<verbose_name_plural lang="en"/>
		<help lang="de">Unterschiedliche Geräte können verschiedene Dateiformate ausgeben, die teilweise untereinander nicht kompatibel sind. Zusätzlich haben einige Gerätehersteller proprietäre Dateiformate. Bei der Wahl des Dateiformats empfiehlt es sich, möglichst standardisierte, nicht-proprietäre und in der Chemie verbreitete Formate zu nutzen. Die Rohdaten sollten Sie zusätzlich im Original-Dateiformat erhalten, wenn es die Dateigröße zulässt.</help>
		<text lang="de">Welche Datentypen, im Sinne von Datenformaten entstehen in Ihrem Projekt?</text>
		<default_text lang="de"/>
		<verbose_name lang="de"/>
		<verbose_name_plural lang="de"/>
		<default_option/>
		<default_external_id/>
		<widget_type>checkbox</widget_type>
		<value_type>option</value_type>
		<maximum/>
		<minimum/>
		<step/>
		<unit/>
		<width/>
		<optionsets>
			<optionset dc:uri="https://rdmo.nfdi4chem.de/terms/options/NFDI_formats"/>
		</optionsets>
		<conditions/>
	</question>
	<question dc:uri="https://rdmo.nfdi4chem.de/terms/questions/NFDI4Chem_Vorlage/data_description/technical_description/ds_usage_how">
		<uri_prefix>https://rdmo.nfdi4chem.de/terms</uri_prefix>
		<key>ds_usage_how</key>
		<path>NFDI4Chem_Vorlage/data_description/technical_description/ds_usage_how</path>
		<dc:comment/>
		<attribute dc:uri="https://rdmorganiser.github.io/terms/domain/project/dataset/usage_description"/>
		<questionset dc:uri="https://rdmo.nfdi4chem.de/terms/questions/NFDI4Chem_Vorlage/data_description/technical_description"/>
		<is_collection>False</is_collection>
		<is_optional>False</is_optional>
		<order>1</order>
		<help lang="en">The following questions may help: What characterisation/analysis methods do you
use? What are the steps involved in your approach? You may have recorded the steps in
your laboratory notebook, if you use one. In a future version of the checklist, you will be able
to link the steps to sample identifiers and generate an overview.</help>
		<text lang="en">And in what way is the data further processed in your project?</text>
		<default_text lang="en"/>
		<verbose_name lang="en"/>
		<verbose_name_plural lang="en"/>
		<help lang="de">Hilfestellungen können folgende Fragen geben:
Welche Charakterisierungs-/ Analysemethoden kommen bei Ihnen zum Einsatz?
Welche einzelnen Arbeitsschritte werden bei Ihrem Vorgehen durchlaufen?
Schauen Sie hierzu bitte auch in Ihrem Laborbuch, wenn Sie eins benutzen, nach. In der
Regel haben Sie hier die einzelnen Arbeitsschritte notiert. In einer späteren Version der
Checkliste können Sie hier die einzelnen Arbeitsschritte den Probenkennzeichnungen
zuordnen und eine Übersicht erzeugen.</help>
		<text lang="de">Auf welche Weise werden die Daten in Ihrem Projekt weiterverarbeitet?</text>
		<default_text lang="de"/>
		<verbose_name lang="de"/>
		<verbose_name_plural lang="de"/>
		<default_option/>
		<default_external_id/>
		<widget_type>textarea</widget_type>
		<value_type>text</value_type>
		<maximum/>
		<minimum/>
		<step/>
		<unit/>
		<width/>
		<optionsets/>
		<conditions/>
	</question>
	<question dc:uri="https://rdmo.nfdi4chem.de/terms/questions/NFDI4Chem_Vorlage/data_description/technical_description/ds_size">
		<uri_prefix>https://rdmo.nfdi4chem.de/terms</uri_prefix>
		<key>ds_size</key>
		<path>NFDI4Chem_Vorlage/data_description/technical_description/ds_size</path>
		<dc:comment/>
		<attribute dc:uri="https://rdmorganiser.github.io/terms/domain/project/dataset/size/volume"/>
		<questionset dc:uri="https://rdmo.nfdi4chem.de/terms/questions/NFDI4Chem_Vorlage/data_description/technical_description"/>
		<is_collection>False</is_collection>
		<is_optional>False</is_optional>
		<order>2</order>
		<help lang="en">Please also state the unit of measure.</help>
		<text lang="en">To what extent do these arise or what is the anticipated data volume?</text>
		<default_text lang="en"/>
		<verbose_name lang="en"/>
		<verbose_name_plural lang="en"/>
		<help lang="de">Geben Sie bitte außerdem die Maßeinheit an.</help>
		<text lang="de">In welchem Umfang fallen diese für Ihren Datensatz an bzw. welches Datenvolumen ist für den Datensatz zu erwarten?</text>
		<default_text lang="de"/>
		<verbose_name lang="de"/>
		<verbose_name_plural lang="de"/>
		<default_option/>
		<default_external_id/>
		<widget_type>radio</widget_type>
		<value_type>option</value_type>
		<maximum/>
		<minimum/>
		<step/>
		<unit/>
		<width/>
		<optionsets>
			<optionset dc:uri="https://rdmo.nfdi4chem.de/terms/options/NFDI_dataset_size"/>
		</optionsets>
		<conditions/>
	</question>
	<section dc:uri="https://rdmo.nfdi4chem.de/terms/questions/NFDI4Chem_Vorlage/doku_quality">
		<uri_prefix>https://rdmo.nfdi4chem.de/terms</uri_prefix>
		<key>doku_quality</key>
		<path>NFDI4Chem_Vorlage/doku_quality</path>
		<dc:comment/>
		<catalog dc:uri="https://rdmo.nfdi4chem.de/terms/questions/NFDI4Chem_Vorlage"/>
		<order>1</order>
		<title lang="en">Documentation and data quality</title>
		<title lang="de">Dokumentation und Datenqualität</title>
	</section>
	<questionset dc:uri="https://rdmo.nfdi4chem.de/terms/questions/NFDI4Chem_Vorlage/doku_quality/dokumentation">
		<uri_prefix>https://rdmo.nfdi4chem.de/terms</uri_prefix>
		<key>dokumentation</key>
		<path>NFDI4Chem_Vorlage/doku_quality/dokumentation</path>
		<dc:comment/>
		<attribute dc:uri="https://rdmorganiser.github.io/terms/domain/project/dataset/id"/>
		<section dc:uri="https://rdmo.nfdi4chem.de/terms/questions/NFDI4Chem_Vorlage/doku_quality"/>
		<questionset/>
		<is_collection>True</is_collection>
		<order>0</order>
		<title lang="en">Dokumentation</title>
		<help lang="en"/>
		<verbose_name lang="en"/>
		<verbose_name_plural lang="en"/>
		<title lang="de">Dokumentation</title>
		<help lang="de"/>
		<verbose_name lang="de"/>
		<verbose_name_plural lang="de"/>
		<conditions/>
	</questionset>
	<question dc:uri="https://rdmo.nfdi4chem.de/terms/questions/NFDI4Chem_Vorlage/doku_quality/dokumentation/dokumentation_standard">
		<uri_prefix>https://rdmo.nfdi4chem.de/terms</uri_prefix>
		<key>dokumentation_standard</key>
		<path>NFDI4Chem_Vorlage/doku_quality/dokumentation/dokumentation_standard</path>
		<dc:comment/>
		<attribute dc:uri="https://rdmorganiser.github.io/terms/domain/project/dataset/metadata/standards"/>
		<questionset dc:uri="https://rdmo.nfdi4chem.de/terms/questions/NFDI4Chem_Vorlage/doku_quality/dokumentation"/>
		<is_collection>True</is_collection>
		<is_optional>False</is_optional>
		<order>0</order>
		<help lang="en">In chemistry, one of the most common methods for documenting data is the laboratory
notebook, either electronic or paper-based. The information is often recorded in a structured
way as metadata. The metadata fields are partly determined by the lab notebook, partly
defined by the user. For the choice of the fields it is recommended to follow the scheme of
the target repository (examples: &lt;a href="https://www.chemotion-repository.net/welcome" target="_blank"&gt;Chemotion&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;a href="https://www.crystallography.net/cod/" target="_blank"&gt;Crystallography Open Database&lt;/a&gt;) or qualified
recommendations, such as
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://knowledgebase.nfdi4chem.de/knowledge_base/docs/metadata/?_highlight=michi#minimum-information-for-chemical-investigations-michi" target="_blank"&gt;NFDI4Chem Knowledge Base&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://schema.org/MolecularEntity" target="_blank"&gt;schema.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Subject- and application-specific initiatives such as &lt;a href="https://nmrml.org/" target="_blank"&gt;nmrML&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
If you need further assistance, please contact the &lt;a href="mailto:helpdesk@nfdi4chem.de" target="_blank"&gt;NFDI4Chem Helpdesk&lt;/a&gt;.</help>
		<text lang="en">What approaches are being taken to describe the data in a comprehensible manner (such as the use of available metadata, documentation standards or ontologies)?</text>
		<default_text lang="en"/>
		<verbose_name lang="en"/>
		<verbose_name_plural lang="en"/>
		<help lang="de">In der Chemie ist eine der gängigsten Methoden zur Datendokumentation das
Laborbuch - elektronisch oder papierbasiert. In beiden Fällen werden die enthaltenen
Informationen strukturiert durch Metadaten erfasst. Je nach Art des Laborbuchs sind
Metadatenfelder vorgegeben oder müssen durch den Nutzenden definiert werden. Bei der
Wahl der Felder wird empfohlen, sich an das Schema des Zielrepositoriums (Beispiele:
&lt;a href="https://www.chemotion-repository.net/welcome" target="_blank"&gt;Chemotion&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="https://www.crystallography.net/cod/" target="_blank"&gt;Crystallography Open Database&lt;/a&gt;) oder an qualifizierte Empfehlungen zu orientieren, wie
z. B.
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://knowledgebase.nfdi4chem.de/knowledge_base/docs/metadata/?_highlight=michi#minimum-information-for-chemical-investigations-michi" target="_blank"&gt;NFDI4Chem Knowledge Base&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://schema.org/MolecularEntity" target="_blank"&gt;schema.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://nmrml.org/" target="_blank"&gt;fach- und anwendungsspezifische Initiativen wie nmrML&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
Wenn Sie weitere Hilfe benötigen, wenden Sie sich bitte an das &lt;a href="mailto:helpdesk@nfdi4chem.de" target="_blank"&gt;NFDI4Chem Helpdesk&lt;/a&gt;.</help>
		<text lang="de">Welche Ansätze werden verfolgt, um die Daten nachvollziehbar zu beschreiben (z. B. Nutzung vorhandener Metadaten- bzw. Dokumentationsstandards oder Ontologien)?</text>
		<default_text lang="de"/>
		<verbose_name lang="de"/>
		<verbose_name_plural lang="de"/>
		<default_option/>
		<default_external_id/>
		<widget_type>checkbox</widget_type>
		<value_type>option</value_type>
		<maximum/>
		<minimum/>
		<step/>
		<unit/>
		<width/>
		<optionsets>
			<optionset dc:uri="https://rdmo.nfdi4chem.de/terms/options/NFDI_description_standards"/>
		</optionsets>
		<conditions/>
	</question>
	<question dc:uri="https://rdmo.nfdi4chem.de/terms/questions/NFDI4Chem_Vorlage/doku_quality/dokumentation/data_usage">
		<uri_prefix>https://rdmo.nfdi4chem.de/terms</uri_prefix>
		<key>data_usage</key>
		<path>NFDI4Chem_Vorlage/doku_quality/dokumentation/data_usage</path>
		<dc:comment/>
		<attribute dc:uri="https://rdmorganiser.github.io/terms/domain/project/dataset/usage_technology"/>
		<questionset dc:uri="https://rdmo.nfdi4chem.de/terms/questions/NFDI4Chem_Vorlage/doku_quality/dokumentation"/>
		<is_collection>True</is_collection>
		<is_optional>False</is_optional>
		<order>1</order>
		<help lang="en">The use of digital methods and tools enables chemists to collect, analyse, interpret,
and derive new scientific insights from experimental data. To make these insights usable by
others, it is important to document the software, equipment, etc. Also, please refer back to
the question regarding data formats.</help>
		<text lang="en">What digital methods and tools (e.g. software) are required to use the data?</text>
		<default_text lang="en"/>
		<verbose_name lang="en"/>
		<verbose_name_plural lang="en"/>
		<help lang="de">Die Nutzung digitaler Methoden und Werkzeuge ermöglicht es Chemikerinnen und
Chemikern, experimentelle Daten zu sammeln, zu analysieren, zu interpretieren und daraus
neue wissenschaftliche Erkenntnisse zu gewinnen. Um diese Erkenntnisse durch andere
nutzbar zu machen, ist es wichtig, die Software, Geräte, usw. zu dokumentieren. Vergleichen
Sie hierzu auch nochmal die Frage zu den Dateiformaten.</help>
		<text lang="de">Welche digitalen Methoden und Werkzeuge (z. B. Software) sind zur Nutzung der Daten erforderlich?</text>
		<default_text lang="de"/>
		<verbose_name lang="de"/>
		<verbose_name_plural lang="de"/>
		<default_option/>
		<default_external_id/>
		<widget_type>checkbox</widget_type>
		<value_type>option</value_type>
		<maximum/>
		<minimum/>
		<step/>
		<unit/>
		<width/>
		<optionsets>
			<optionset dc:uri="https://rdmo.nfdi4chem.de/terms/options/NFDI_software"/>
		</optionsets>
		<conditions/>
	</question>
	<questionset dc:uri="https://rdmo.nfdi4chem.de/terms/questions/NFDI4Chem_Vorlage/doku_quality/data_quality">
		<uri_prefix>https://rdmo.nfdi4chem.de/terms</uri_prefix>
		<key>data_quality</key>
		<path>NFDI4Chem_Vorlage/doku_quality/data_quality</path>
		<dc:comment/>
		<attribute dc:uri="https://rdmorganiser.github.io/terms/domain/project/dataset/id"/>
		<section dc:uri="https://rdmo.nfdi4chem.de/terms/questions/NFDI4Chem_Vorlage/doku_quality"/>
		<questionset/>
		<is_collection>True</is_collection>
		<order>1</order>
		<title lang="en">Data Quality</title>
		<help lang="en"/>
		<verbose_name lang="en"/>
		<verbose_name_plural lang="en"/>
		<title lang="de">Datenqualität</title>
		<help lang="de"/>
		<verbose_name lang="de"/>
		<verbose_name_plural lang="de"/>
		<conditions/>
	</questionset>
	<question dc:uri="https://rdmo.nfdi4chem.de/terms/questions/NFDI4Chem_Vorlage/doku_quality/data_quality/data_high_quality">
		<uri_prefix>https://rdmo.nfdi4chem.de/terms</uri_prefix>
		<key>data_high_quality</key>
		<path>NFDI4Chem_Vorlage/doku_quality/data_quality/data_high_quality</path>
		<dc:comment/>
		<attribute dc:uri="https://rdmorganiser.github.io/terms/domain/project/dataset/quality_assurance"/>
		<questionset dc:uri="https://rdmo.nfdi4chem.de/terms/questions/NFDI4Chem_Vorlage/doku_quality/data_quality"/>
		<is_collection>True</is_collection>
		<is_optional>False</is_optional>
		<order>0</order>
		<help lang="en">Various measures are implemented in chemistry to ensure data quality. One of the
most well-known methods is the Standard Operating Procedure (SOP), which many
research groups define for their characterisation/analysis methods and workflows.</help>
		<text lang="en">What measures are being adopted to ensure high data quality?</text>
		<default_text lang="en"/>
		<verbose_name lang="en"/>
		<verbose_name_plural lang="en"/>
		<help lang="de">In der Chemie kommen für die Sicherung der Qualität der Daten verschiedene
Maßnahmen zum Tragen. Eine der bekanntesten ist das Standard Operating Procedure
(SOP), welches viele Arbeitskreise für ihre verwendeten Charakterisierungs-/
Analysemethoden und Arbeitsabläufe definiert.</help>
		<text lang="de">Welche Maßnahmen werden getroffen, um eine hohe Qualität der Daten zu gewährleisten?</text>
		<default_text lang="de"/>
		<verbose_name lang="de"/>
		<verbose_name_plural lang="de"/>
		<default_option/>
		<default_external_id/>
		<widget_type>checkbox</widget_type>
		<value_type>option</value_type>
		<maximum/>
		<minimum/>
		<step/>
		<unit/>
		<width/>
		<optionsets>
			<optionset dc:uri="https://rdmo.nfdi4chem.de/terms/options/NFDI_ds_quality"/>
		</optionsets>
		<conditions/>
	</question>
	<question dc:uri="https://rdmo.nfdi4chem.de/terms/questions/NFDI4Chem_Vorlage/doku_quality/data_quality/quality_control">
		<uri_prefix>https://rdmo.nfdi4chem.de/terms</uri_prefix>
		<key>quality_control</key>
		<path>NFDI4Chem_Vorlage/doku_quality/data_quality/quality_control</path>
		<dc:comment/>
		<attribute dc:uri="https://rdmorganiser.github.io/terms/domain/project/dataset/control_tool"/>
		<questionset dc:uri="https://rdmo.nfdi4chem.de/terms/questions/NFDI4Chem_Vorlage/doku_quality/data_quality"/>
		<is_collection>True</is_collection>
		<is_optional>False</is_optional>
		<order>1</order>
		<help lang="en">Quality controls depend on various factors, such as the chemistry subfield and
structures within the institute or project. It is important that quality control is independent of
the measures taken and relates to the product "data." Examples would include: peer review
by a colleague, supervisor, data steward, etc. Or through a tool, checksums, etc. Also,
specify the timing of the quality control(s).</help>
		<text lang="en">Are quality controls in place and if so, how do they operate?</text>
		<default_text lang="en"/>
		<verbose_name lang="en"/>
		<verbose_name_plural lang="en"/>
		<help lang="de">Qualitätskontrollen sind von unterschiedlichen Faktoren wie z.B. dem Teilbereich der
Chemie sowie von Strukturen am Institut oder im Projekt abhängig. Wichtig ist, dass die
Qualitätskontrolle von in der Datenverarbeitung nicht involvierten Akteuren durchgeführt wird
und sich auf das Produkt „Daten“ bezieht. Beispielhaft wäre hier zu nennen: durch eine
Begutachtung einer/s Kollegin/en, Vorgesetzten, Data Steward, …. Oder auch durch ein
Tool, Checksummen, ….

Legen Sie außerdem den Zeitpunkt der Qualitätskontrolle oder der Kontrollen fest.</help>
		<text lang="de">Sind Qualitätskontrollen vorgesehen und wenn ja, auf welche Weise?</text>
		<default_text lang="de"/>
		<verbose_name lang="de"/>
		<verbose_name_plural lang="de"/>
		<default_option/>
		<default_external_id/>
		<widget_type>checkbox</widget_type>
		<value_type>option</value_type>
		<maximum/>
		<minimum/>
		<step/>
		<unit/>
		<width/>
		<optionsets>
			<optionset dc:uri="https://rdmo.nfdi4chem.de/terms/options/quality_control"/>
		</optionsets>
		<conditions/>
	</question>
	<section dc:uri="https://rdmo.nfdi4chem.de/terms/questions/NFDI4Chem_Vorlage/storage_backup">
		<uri_prefix>https://rdmo.nfdi4chem.de/terms</uri_prefix>
		<key>storage_backup</key>
		<path>NFDI4Chem_Vorlage/storage_backup</path>
		<dc:comment/>
		<catalog dc:uri="https://rdmo.nfdi4chem.de/terms/questions/NFDI4Chem_Vorlage"/>
		<order>2</order>
		<title lang="en">Storage and Technical Security During the Project</title>
		<title lang="de">Speicherung und technische Sicherung während des Projektverlaufs</title>
	</section>
	<questionset dc:uri="https://rdmo.nfdi4chem.de/terms/questions/NFDI4Chem_Vorlage/storage_backup/data_storage">
		<uri_prefix>https://rdmo.nfdi4chem.de/terms</uri_prefix>
		<key>data_storage</key>
		<path>NFDI4Chem_Vorlage/storage_backup/data_storage</path>
		<dc:comment/>
		<attribute dc:uri="https://rdmorganiser.github.io/terms/domain/project/dataset/id"/>
		<section dc:uri="https://rdmo.nfdi4chem.de/terms/questions/NFDI4Chem_Vorlage/storage_backup"/>
		<questionset/>
		<is_collection>True</is_collection>
		<order>0</order>
		<title lang="en">Data Storage during the Project</title>
		<help lang="en"/>
		<verbose_name lang="en"/>
		<verbose_name_plural lang="en"/>
		<title lang="de">Datenspeicherung während des Projekts</title>
		<help lang="de"/>
		<verbose_name lang="de"/>
		<verbose_name_plural lang="de"/>
		<conditions/>
	</questionset>
	<question dc:uri="https://rdmo.nfdi4chem.de/terms/questions/NFDI4Chem_Vorlage/storage_backup/data_storage/data_storage_how">
		<uri_prefix>https://rdmo.nfdi4chem.de/terms</uri_prefix>
		<key>data_storage_how</key>
		<path>NFDI4Chem_Vorlage/storage_backup/data_storage/data_storage_how</path>
		<dc:comment/>
		<attribute dc:uri="https://rdmorganiser.github.io/terms/domain/project/dataset/storage/type"/>
		<questionset dc:uri="https://rdmo.nfdi4chem.de/terms/questions/NFDI4Chem_Vorlage/storage_backup/data_storage"/>
		<is_collection>True</is_collection>
		<is_optional>False</is_optional>
		<order>0</order>
		<help lang="en">This question deals with storage of "hot data" during the period when you are actively
working with the data. Where and how you store research data depends on your local
working routines and systems and from the actors who need access to the data (possibly
external partners). Advantages and disadvantages of different storage media can be found at
&lt;a href="https://www.forschungsdaten.info/themen/speichern-und-rechnen/datenspeicherung-und-di
e-lebensdauer-von-datentraegern/" target="_blank"&gt;forschungsdaten.info&lt;/a&gt;. In order to prevent data loss, it is also recommended to
follow the 3-2-1 rule for data storage: 3 copies of the data, among them 2 on different media
types, and 1 offline copy.</help>
		<text lang="en">How is the data to be stored and archived throughout the project duration?</text>
		<default_text lang="en"/>
		<verbose_name lang="en"/>
		<verbose_name_plural lang="en"/>
		<help lang="de">In dieser Frage geht es um die zwischenzeitliche Speicherung von Daten für die Zeit,
in der Sie aktiv mit den Daten arbeiten. Wo und wie Sie die Forschungsdaten speichern,
hängt ab von Ihren Arbeitsroutinen und Systemen vor Ort und von den Akteuren, die einen
Zugang zu den Daten brauchen (womöglich externe Partner). Vor- und Nachteile
unterschiedlicher Speichermedien finden Sie auf forschungsdaten.info
(&lt;a href="https://www.forschungsdaten.info/themen/speichern-und-rechnen/datenspeicherung-und-di
e-lebensdauer-von-datentraegern/" target="_blank"&gt;https://www.forschungsdaten.info/themen/speichern-und-rechnen/datenspeicherung-und-di
e-lebensdauer-von-datentraegern/&lt;/a&gt;). Empfehlenswert, um Datenverlust zu vermeiden, ist
ebenfalls die 3-2-1-Regel: 3 Kopien der Daten davon 2 auf verschiedenen Medientypen und
1 Kopie offline.</help>
		<text lang="de">Auf welche Weise werden die Daten während der Projektlaufzeit gespeichert und gesichert?</text>
		<default_text lang="de"/>
		<verbose_name lang="de"/>
		<verbose_name_plural lang="de"/>
		<default_option/>
		<default_external_id/>
		<widget_type>checkbox</widget_type>
		<value_type>option</value_type>
		<maximum/>
		<minimum/>
		<step/>
		<unit/>
		<width/>
		<optionsets>
			<optionset dc:uri="https://rdmo.nfdi4chem.de/terms/options/NFDI_storage"/>
		</optionsets>
		<conditions/>
	</question>
	<question dc:uri="https://rdmo.nfdi4chem.de/terms/questions/NFDI4Chem_Vorlage/storage_backup/data_storage/data_connection">
		<uri_prefix>https://rdmo.nfdi4chem.de/terms</uri_prefix>
		<key>data_connection</key>
		<path>NFDI4Chem_Vorlage/storage_backup/data_storage/data_connection</path>
		<dc:comment/>
		<attribute dc:uri="https://rdmorganiser.github.io/terms/domain/project/dataset/metadata/references_to_other_data"/>
		<questionset dc:uri="https://rdmo.nfdi4chem.de/terms/questions/NFDI4Chem_Vorlage/storage_backup/data_storage"/>
		<is_collection>True</is_collection>
		<is_optional>False</is_optional>
		<order>1</order>
		<help lang="en">In addition to proper documentation, linking physical samples to experimental data
plays a crucial role in ensuring reproducibility, quality assurance, and analysis of research
results. The linking process depends on the targets and requirements of a project, especially
if there are no specific plans from your institution.</help>
		<text lang="en">How are the generated or existing physical samples linked to the data during the project's duration?</text>
		<default_text lang="en"/>
		<verbose_name lang="en"/>
		<verbose_name_plural lang="en"/>
		<help lang="de">Neben der ordnungsgemäßen Dokumentation spielt für die Reproduzierbarkeit,
Qualitätssicherung und Analyse von Forschungsergebnissen auch die Verknüpfung von
physischen Proben mit den experimentellen Daten eine entscheidende Rolle. Die
Verknüpfung ist, wenn es keine konkreten Pläne von Ihrer Institution gibt, abhängig von den
Zielen und Anforderungen eines Projekts.</help>
		<text lang="de">Auf welche Weise werden die erzeugten oder bestehenden physischen Proben während der Projektlaufzeit mit den Daten verknüpft?</text>
		<default_text lang="de"/>
		<verbose_name lang="de"/>
		<verbose_name_plural lang="de"/>
		<default_option/>
		<default_external_id/>
		<widget_type>checkbox</widget_type>
		<value_type>option</value_type>
		<maximum/>
		<minimum/>
		<step/>
		<unit/>
		<width/>
		<optionsets>
			<optionset dc:uri="https://rdmo.nfdi4chem.de/terms/options/data_connection"/>
		</optionsets>
		<conditions/>
	</question>
	<questionset dc:uri="https://rdmo.nfdi4chem.de/terms/questions/NFDI4Chem_Vorlage/storage_backup/data_backup">
		<uri_prefix>https://rdmo.nfdi4chem.de/terms</uri_prefix>
		<key>data_backup</key>
		<path>NFDI4Chem_Vorlage/storage_backup/data_backup</path>
		<dc:comment/>
		<attribute dc:uri="https://rdmorganiser.github.io/terms/domain/project/dataset/id"/>
		<section dc:uri="https://rdmo.nfdi4chem.de/terms/questions/NFDI4Chem_Vorlage/storage_backup"/>
		<questionset/>
		<is_collection>True</is_collection>
		<order>1</order>
		<title lang="en">Technical Data Security during the Project</title>
		<help lang="en"/>
		<verbose_name lang="en"/>
		<verbose_name_plural lang="en"/>
		<title lang="de">Technische Datensicherung während des Projekts</title>
		<help lang="de"/>
		<verbose_name lang="de"/>
		<verbose_name_plural lang="de"/>
		<conditions/>
	</questionset>
	<question dc:uri="https://rdmo.nfdi4chem.de/terms/questions/NFDI4Chem_Vorlage/storage_backup/data_backup/sensitive_data_security">
		<uri_prefix>https://rdmo.nfdi4chem.de/terms</uri_prefix>
		<key>sensitive_data_security</key>
		<path>NFDI4Chem_Vorlage/storage_backup/data_backup/sensitive_data_security</path>
		<dc:comment/>
		<attribute dc:uri="https://rdmorganiser.github.io/terms/domain/project/dataset/data_security/security_measures"/>
		<questionset dc:uri="https://rdmo.nfdi4chem.de/terms/questions/NFDI4Chem_Vorlage/storage_backup/data_backup"/>
		<is_collection>False</is_collection>
		<is_optional>False</is_optional>
		<order>0</order>
		<help lang="en">When discussing sensitive data in chemistry, these data are typically not personal
data. Sensitive data often arise in projects with industrial collaborations. Data may become
sensitive during a project when considerations about patenting arise. Access and usage
rights are then documented in confidentiality agreements, known as Non-Disclosure
Agreements (NDAs). Explain here how you regulate access, especially if you have
restrictions, and mention the tools you use. 

Please also note the question on the next page, which deals with the legal peculiarities and where you can
go into more detail about the reasons for these restrictions. If you have questions about
ethical, legal, and social aspects, the &lt;a href="https://www.nfdi.de/section-elsa/" target="_blank"&gt;ELSA section&lt;/a&gt; can support you.</help>
		<text lang="en">What is in place to secure sensitive data in this dataset throughout the project duration (access and usage rights)?</text>
		<default_text lang="en"/>
		<verbose_name lang="en"/>
		<verbose_name_plural lang="en"/>
		<help lang="de">Wenn wir in der Chemie über sensible Daten sprechen, sind diese in der Regel keine
personenbezogenen Daten. Sensible Daten treten meistens in Projekten mit
Industriekooperationen auf. Daten können während eines Projektes sensibel werden, wenn
Überlegungen zur Patentierung aufkommen. Die Zugriffs- und Nutzungsrechte werden dann
in Geheimhaltungserklärungen, sogenannten Non-Disclosure Agreements (NDS)
festgehalten. Erklären Sie hier, wenn Sie Einschränkungen haben, wie Sie die Zugriffe
regeln. Z.B. auch welches Tool Sie dafür verwenden.

Bitte beachten Sie auch die Frage auf der nächsten Seite, die auf die rechtlichen Besonderheiten eingeht und bei der Sie noch einmal genauer auf die Gründe der
Einschränkung eingehen können. Bei Fragen zu ethischen, rechtlichen und sozialen Aspekten unterstützt Sie die Sektion
&lt;a href="https://www.nfdi.de/section-elsa/" target="_blank"&gt;ELSA&lt;/a&gt;.</help>
		<text lang="de">Wie wird die Sicherheit sensibler Daten in diesem Datenset während der Projektlaufzeit gewährleistet (Zugriffs- und Nutzungsverwaltung)?</text>
		<default_text lang="de"/>
		<verbose_name lang="de"/>
		<verbose_name_plural lang="de"/>
		<default_option/>
		<default_external_id/>
		<widget_type>textarea</widget_type>
		<value_type>text</value_type>
		<maximum/>
		<minimum/>
		<step/>
		<unit/>
		<width/>
		<optionsets/>
		<conditions/>
	</question>
	<section dc:uri="https://rdmo.nfdi4chem.de/terms/questions/NFDI4Chem_Vorlage/exchange_access">
		<uri_prefix>https://rdmo.nfdi4chem.de/terms</uri_prefix>
		<key>exchange_access</key>
		<path>NFDI4Chem_Vorlage/exchange_access</path>
		<dc:comment/>
		<catalog dc:uri="https://rdmo.nfdi4chem.de/terms/questions/NFDI4Chem_Vorlage"/>
		<order>3</order>
		<title lang="en">Data Exchange and long-term Data Accessibility</title>
		<title lang="de">Datenaustausch und dauerhafte Zugänglichkeit der Daten</title>
	</section>
	<questionset dc:uri="https://rdmo.nfdi4chem.de/terms/questions/NFDI4Chem_Vorlage/exchange_access/reuse">
		<uri_prefix>https://rdmo.nfdi4chem.de/terms</uri_prefix>
		<key>reuse</key>
		<path>NFDI4Chem_Vorlage/exchange_access/reuse</path>
		<dc:comment/>
		<attribute dc:uri="https://rdmorganiser.github.io/terms/domain/project/dataset/id"/>
		<section dc:uri="https://rdmo.nfdi4chem.de/terms/questions/NFDI4Chem_Vorlage/exchange_access"/>
		<questionset/>
		<is_collection>True</is_collection>
		<order>0</order>
		<title lang="en">Reuse</title>
		<help lang="en"/>
		<verbose_name lang="en"/>
		<verbose_name_plural lang="en"/>
		<title lang="de">Nachnutzung</title>
		<help lang="de"/>
		<verbose_name lang="de"/>
		<verbose_name_plural lang="de"/>
		<conditions/>
	</questionset>
	<question dc:uri="https://rdmo.nfdi4chem.de/terms/questions/NFDI4Chem_Vorlage/exchange_access/reuse/reuse_context">
		<uri_prefix>https://rdmo.nfdi4chem.de/terms</uri_prefix>
		<key>reuse_context</key>
		<path>NFDI4Chem_Vorlage/exchange_access/reuse/reuse_context</path>
		<dc:comment/>
		<attribute dc:uri="https://rdmorganiser.github.io/terms/domain/project/dataset/reuse_scenario"/>
		<questionset dc:uri="https://rdmo.nfdi4chem.de/terms/questions/NFDI4Chem_Vorlage/exchange_access/reuse"/>
		<is_collection>True</is_collection>
		<is_optional>False</is_optional>
		<order>0</order>
		<help lang="en">Due to the fundamental role of chemistry in other fields, please consider whether your
data can be reused.</help>
		<text lang="en">Is this data set especially suitable for use in other contexts?</text>
		<default_text lang="en"/>
		<verbose_name lang="en"/>
		<verbose_name_plural lang="en"/>
		<help lang="de">Durch die fundamentale Rolle der Chemie und die Überschneidungen zu anderen
Wissenschaftsbereichen, wägen Sie bitte ab, ob Ihre Daten nachgenutzt werden können.
(Vgl. Sie dazu auch die nachfolgende Frage.)</help>
		<text lang="de">Bietet sich dieser Datensatz für die Nachnutzung in anderen Kontexten an?</text>
		<default_text lang="de"/>
		<verbose_name lang="de"/>
		<verbose_name_plural lang="de"/>
		<default_option/>
		<default_external_id/>
		<widget_type>checkbox</widget_type>
		<value_type>option</value_type>
		<maximum/>
		<minimum/>
		<step/>
		<unit/>
		<width/>
		<optionsets>
			<optionset dc:uri="https://rdmo.nfdi4chem.de/terms/options/NFDI_reuse_context"/>
		</optionsets>
		<conditions/>
	</question>
	<question dc:uri="https://rdmo.nfdi4chem.de/terms/questions/NFDI4Chem_Vorlage/exchange_access/reuse/reuse_criteria">
		<uri_prefix>https://rdmo.nfdi4chem.de/terms</uri_prefix>
		<key>reuse_criteria</key>
		<path>NFDI4Chem_Vorlage/exchange_access/reuse/reuse_criteria</path>
		<dc:comment/>
		<attribute dc:uri="https://rdmorganiser.github.io/terms/domain/project/preservation/selection_criteria"/>
		<questionset dc:uri="https://rdmo.nfdi4chem.de/terms/questions/NFDI4Chem_Vorlage/exchange_access/reuse"/>
		<is_collection>True</is_collection>
		<is_optional>False</is_optional>
		<order>1</order>
		<help lang="en"/>
		<text lang="en">Which criteria are used to select research data to make it available for subsequent use by others?</text>
		<default_text lang="en"/>
		<verbose_name lang="en"/>
		<verbose_name_plural lang="en"/>
		<help lang="de"/>
		<text lang="de">Nach welchen Kriterien wird dieser Datensatz ausgewählt, um diesen für die Nachnutzung durch andere zur Verfügung zu stellen?</text>
		<default_text lang="de"/>
		<verbose_name lang="de"/>
		<verbose_name_plural lang="de"/>
		<default_option/>
		<default_external_id/>
		<widget_type>checkbox</widget_type>
		<value_type>option</value_type>
		<maximum/>
		<minimum/>
		<step/>
		<unit/>
		<width/>
		<optionsets>
			<optionset dc:uri="https://rdmo.nfdi4chem.de/terms/options/NFDI_reuse_motivation"/>
		</optionsets>
		<conditions/>
	</question>
	<question dc:uri="https://rdmo.nfdi4chem.de/terms/questions/NFDI4Chem_Vorlage/exchange_access/reuse/reuse_when">
		<uri_prefix>https://rdmo.nfdi4chem.de/terms</uri_prefix>
		<key>reuse_when</key>
		<path>NFDI4Chem_Vorlage/exchange_access/reuse/reuse_when</path>
		<dc:comment/>
		<attribute dc:uri="https://rdmorganiser.github.io/terms/domain/project/dataset/data_publication_date"/>
		<questionset dc:uri="https://rdmo.nfdi4chem.de/terms/questions/NFDI4Chem_Vorlage/exchange_access/reuse"/>
		<is_collection>False</is_collection>
		<is_optional>False</is_optional>
		<order>2</order>
		<help lang="en">According to the DFG's "&lt;a href="https://www.dfg.de/download/pdf/foerderung/grundlagen_dfg_foerderung/forschungsdaten/l
eitlinien_forschungsdaten.pdf" target="_blank"&gt;Guidelines for Research Data Management&lt;/a&gt;", research data should be made available as soon as possible
and, in the best case, follow the &lt;a href="https://force11.org/info/guiding-principles-for-findable-accessible-interoperable-and-re-usabl
e-data-publishing-version-b1-0/" target="_blank"&gt;FAIR principles&lt;/a&gt; of Findability, Accessibility, Interoperability,
Re-Usability. The importance of data publication is also emphasised in
Guideline 13 of the Code of Good Scientific Practice "&lt;a href="https://wissenschaftliche-integritaet.de/kodex/herstellung-von-offentlichem-zugang-zu-forsc
hungsergebnissen/" target="_blank"&gt;Public Access to Research Results&lt;/a&gt;". It points to discipline-specific practices.
For the publication of research data, it is recommended to use discipline-specific
repositories. Recommended directories to find a suitable repository include:
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://search.nfdi4chem.de" target="_blank"&gt;NFDI4Chem Search Service&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.re3data.org/" target="_blank"&gt;Re3data.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://fairsharing.org/" target="_blank"&gt;FAIRSharing.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</help>
		<text lang="en">When is the research data available for use by third parties?</text>
		<default_text lang="en"/>
		<verbose_name lang="en"/>
		<verbose_name_plural lang="en"/>
		<help lang="de">Den &lt;a href="https://www.dfg.de/download/pdf/foerderung/grundlagen_dfg_foerderung/forschungsdaten/l
eitlinien_forschungsdaten.pdf" target="_blank"&gt;DFG–Leitlinien zum Forschungsdatenmanagement&lt;/a&gt; entsprechend sollten Forschungsdaten so früh wie möglich
verfügbar gemacht werden und konform zu den &lt;a href="https://force11.org/info/guiding-principles-for-findable-accessible-interoperable-and-re-usabl
e-data-publishing-version-b1-0/" target="_blank"&gt;FAIR-Data-Prinzipien&lt;/a&gt; der Auffindbarkeit,
Zugänglichkeit, Interoperativität und Nachnutzbarkeit sein. Die Bedeutung der Datenpublikation wird auch
nochmal unterstrichen durch die Leitlinie 13 des Kodex zur Guten Wissenschaftlichen Praxis
"&lt;a href="https://wissenschaftliche-integritaet.de/kodex/herstellung-von-offentlichem-zugang-zu-forsch
ungsergebnissen/" target="_blank"&gt;Herstellung von öffentlichem Zugang zu Forschungsergebnissen&lt;/a&gt;". Hier wird auf die disziplinspezifischen Gepflogenheiten hingewiesen.

Für die Publikation von Forschungsdaten wird empfohlen, bevorzugt fachspezifische
Repositorien zu nutzen. Empfehlenswerte Verzeichnisse für die Suche eines Repositoriums
sind:
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://search.nfdi4chem.de" target="_blank"&gt;NFDI4Chem Search Service&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.re3data.org/" target="_blank"&gt;Re3data.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://fairsharing.org/" target="_blank"&gt;FAIRSharing.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</help>
		<text lang="de">Wann ist dieser Datensatz für Dritte nutzbar?</text>
		<default_text lang="de"/>
		<verbose_name lang="de"/>
		<verbose_name_plural lang="de"/>
		<default_option/>
		<default_external_id/>
		<widget_type>radio</widget_type>
		<value_type>option</value_type>
		<maximum/>
		<minimum/>
		<step/>
		<unit/>
		<width/>
		<optionsets>
			<optionset dc:uri="https://rdmo.nfdi4chem.de/terms/options/NFDI_using_when"/>
		</optionsets>
		<conditions/>
	</question>
	<questionset dc:uri="https://rdmo.nfdi4chem.de/terms/questions/NFDI4Chem_Vorlage/exchange_access/archiving">
		<uri_prefix>https://rdmo.nfdi4chem.de/terms</uri_prefix>
		<key>archiving</key>
		<path>NFDI4Chem_Vorlage/exchange_access/archiving</path>
		<dc:comment/>
		<attribute dc:uri="https://rdmorganiser.github.io/terms/domain/project/dataset/id"/>
		<section dc:uri="https://rdmo.nfdi4chem.de/terms/questions/NFDI4Chem_Vorlage/exchange_access"/>
		<questionset/>
		<is_collection>True</is_collection>
		<order>1</order>
		<title lang="en">Archiving</title>
		<help lang="en"/>
		<verbose_name lang="en"/>
		<verbose_name_plural lang="en"/>
		<title lang="de">Archivierung</title>
		<help lang="de"/>
		<verbose_name lang="de"/>
		<verbose_name_plural lang="de"/>
		<conditions/>
	</questionset>
	<question dc:uri="https://rdmo.nfdi4chem.de/terms/questions/NFDI4Chem_Vorlage/exchange_access/archiving/archiving_infrastructure">
		<uri_prefix>https://rdmo.nfdi4chem.de/terms</uri_prefix>
		<key>archiving_infrastructure</key>
		<path>NFDI4Chem_Vorlage/exchange_access/archiving/archiving_infrastructure</path>
		<dc:comment/>
		<attribute dc:uri="https://rdmorganiser.github.io/terms/domain/project/dataset/preservation/repository"/>
		<questionset dc:uri="https://rdmo.nfdi4chem.de/terms/questions/NFDI4Chem_Vorlage/exchange_access/archiving"/>
		<is_collection>True</is_collection>
		<is_optional>False</is_optional>
		<order>0</order>
		<help lang="en">In accordance with good scientific practice, research data must generally be stored for
10 years. (see Guideline 17 of the Code of Good Scientific Practice "&lt;a href="https://wissenschaftliche-integritaet.de/kodex/archivierung/" target="_blank"&gt;Archiving&lt;/a&gt;").

To ensure that the data remains available and retrievable, it must also be maintained beyond
the project. If you archive the data in a data centre or repository, the responsibility is usually
assumed by the operators. Please check or clarify the responsibilities in advance. The
archiving service of your university/research institution may be free of charge for members
and often guarantees secure storage of the data in accordance with the requirements of
good scientific practice. Archiving includes metadata, documentation and any relevant
code/software.</help>
		<text lang="en">How do you archive your data and in which suitable infrastructure?</text>
		<default_text lang="en"/>
		<verbose_name lang="en"/>
		<verbose_name_plural lang="en"/>
		<help lang="de">Entsprechend der Guten Wissenschaftlichen Praxis müssen Forschungsdaten in der
Regel für 10 Jahre aufbewahrt werden (vgl. Sie hierzu die &lt;a href="https://wissenschaftliche-integritaet.de/kodex/archivierung/" target="_blank"&gt;Leitlinie 17&lt;/a&gt; des Kodex zur Guten
Wissenschaftlichen Praxis).

Damit die Daten verfügbar und auffindbar bleiben, müssen diese auch über das Projekt
hinaus gepflegt werden. Archivieren Sie die Daten in einem Datenzentrum oder
-repositorium, wird die Verantwortung in der Regel von den Betreibenden übernommen. Bitte
prüfen bzw. klären Sie vorab die Verantwortlichkeiten. Der Archivdienst Ihrer Universität/
Forschungseinrichtung kann für Angehörige kostenfrei sein und garantiert häufig eine
sichere Aufbewahrung der Daten entsprechend den Anforderungen der Guten
Wissenschaftlichen Praxis. Die Archivierung schließt Metadaten, Dokumentationen und ggf.
relevanten Code/Software mit ein.</help>
		<text lang="de">Wie archivieren Sie Ihre Daten und in welcher geeigneten Infrastruktur?</text>
		<default_text lang="de"/>
		<verbose_name lang="de"/>
		<verbose_name_plural lang="de"/>
		<default_option/>
		<default_external_id/>
		<widget_type>checkbox</widget_type>
		<value_type>option</value_type>
		<maximum/>
		<minimum/>
		<step/>
		<unit/>
		<width/>
		<optionsets>
			<optionset dc:uri="https://rdmo.nfdi4chem.de/terms/options/NFDI_archive"/>
		</optionsets>
		<conditions/>
	</question>
	<question dc:uri="https://rdmo.nfdi4chem.de/terms/questions/NFDI4Chem_Vorlage/exchange_access/archiving/archiving_when">
		<uri_prefix>https://rdmo.nfdi4chem.de/terms</uri_prefix>
		<key>archiving_when</key>
		<path>NFDI4Chem_Vorlage/exchange_access/archiving/archiving_when</path>
		<dc:comment/>
		<attribute dc:uri="https://rdmorganiser.github.io/terms/domain/project/dataset/preservation/embargo_period"/>
		<questionset dc:uri="https://rdmo.nfdi4chem.de/terms/questions/NFDI4Chem_Vorlage/exchange_access/archiving"/>
		<is_collection>False</is_collection>
		<is_optional>False</is_optional>
		<order>1</order>
		<help lang="en">As mentioned above, an embargo or embargo period allows the data to be published
at a later date. Whether the selected repository offers such an embargo/locking period must
be determined in advance.</help>
		<text lang="en">Are embargo periods to be observed? If so, how long are they?</text>
		<default_text lang="en"/>
		<verbose_name lang="en"/>
		<verbose_name_plural lang="en"/>
		<help lang="de">Wie vorher erwähnt, ermöglicht eine Embargo- oder Sperrfrist eine Veröffentlichung
der Daten zu einem späteren Zeitpunkt. Ob das gewählte Repositorium eine solche
Embargo-/Sperrfrist anbietet, muss im Voraus eruiert werden.</help>
		<text lang="de">Sind Sperrfristen zu beachten? Wenn ja, wie lange sind diese?</text>
		<default_text lang="de"/>
		<verbose_name lang="de"/>
		<verbose_name_plural lang="de"/>
		<default_option/>
		<default_external_id/>
		<widget_type>textarea</widget_type>
		<value_type>text</value_type>
		<maximum/>
		<minimum/>
		<step/>
		<unit/>
		<width/>
		<optionsets/>
		<conditions/>
	</question>
	<question dc:uri="https://rdmo.nfdi4chem.de/terms/questions/NFDI4Chem_Vorlage/exchange_access/archiving/sample_archiving">
		<uri_prefix>https://rdmo.nfdi4chem.de/terms</uri_prefix>
		<key>sample_archiving</key>
		<path>NFDI4Chem_Vorlage/exchange_access/archiving/sample_archiving</path>
		<dc:comment/>
		<attribute dc:uri="https://rdmorganiser.github.io/terms/domain/project/other_research_output/plan"/>
		<questionset dc:uri="https://rdmo.nfdi4chem.de/terms/questions/NFDI4Chem_Vorlage/exchange_access/archiving"/>
		<is_collection>False</is_collection>
		<is_optional>False</is_optional>
		<order>2</order>
		<help lang="en">In chemistry, long-term storage of physical samples is often done in the laboratory
itself by means of refrigerators and freezers. An alternative is provided by the central service
&lt;a href="https://www.ioc.kit.edu/braese/1020.php" target="_blank"&gt;ComPlat&lt;/a&gt; at KIT, which offers a central storage of chemical substances.

Linking data and physical samples is important for reproducibility and data quality, both
during the project and after its end. For that purpose a sample database or inventory system,
such as &lt;a href="https://findmolecule.com/" target="_blank"&gt;FindMolecule&lt;/a&gt; may help.</help>
		<text lang="en">How are the physical samples archived, and how are data linked to the physical samples?</text>
		<default_text lang="en"/>
		<verbose_name lang="en"/>
		<verbose_name_plural lang="en"/>
		<help lang="de">In der Chemie erfolgt normalerweise die längerfristige Lagerung der physischen
Proben in Räumlichkeiten des Labors, in dedizierten Kühlschränken und Gefriertruhen. Als
Alternative bietet sich der zentrale Dienst &lt;a href="https://www.ioc.kit.edu/braese/1020.php" target="_blank"&gt;ComPlat&lt;/a&gt; beim KIT, der sich als zentraler Speicher
chemischer Substanzen anbietet.

Die Verknüpfung der Daten mit physischen Proben ist für die Reproduzierbarkeit und
Datenqualität wichtig, sowohl während des Projektes, als auch nach Projektende. Dafür
helfen Probendatenbanken und Inventory Systeme wie z. B. &lt;a href="https://findmolecule.com/inventory/" target="_blank"&gt;FindMolecule&lt;/a&gt;.</help>
		<text lang="de">Wie werden die physischen Proben archiviert und wie werden die Daten mit den physischen Proben verknüpft?</text>
		<default_text lang="de"/>
		<verbose_name lang="de"/>
		<verbose_name_plural lang="de"/>
		<default_option/>
		<default_external_id/>
		<widget_type>textarea</widget_type>
		<value_type>text</value_type>
		<maximum/>
		<minimum/>
		<step/>
		<unit/>
		<width/>
		<optionsets/>
		<conditions/>
	</question>
	<questionset dc:uri="https://rdmo.nfdi4chem.de/terms/questions/NFDI4Chem_Vorlage/exchange_access/publication_restrictions">
		<uri_prefix>https://rdmo.nfdi4chem.de/terms</uri_prefix>
		<key>publication_restrictions</key>
		<path>NFDI4Chem_Vorlage/exchange_access/publication_restrictions</path>
		<dc:comment/>
		<attribute dc:uri="https://rdmorganiser.github.io/terms/domain/project/dataset/id"/>
		<section dc:uri="https://rdmo.nfdi4chem.de/terms/questions/NFDI4Chem_Vorlage/exchange_access"/>
		<questionset/>
		<is_collection>True</is_collection>
		<order>2</order>
		<title lang="en">Restrictions on Publication</title>
		<help lang="en"/>
		<verbose_name lang="en"/>
		<verbose_name_plural lang="en"/>
		<title lang="de">Beschränkungen bei der Veröffentlichung</title>
		<help lang="de"/>
		<verbose_name lang="de"/>
		<verbose_name_plural lang="de"/>
		<conditions/>
	</questionset>
	<question dc:uri="https://rdmo.nfdi4chem.de/terms/questions/NFDI4Chem_Vorlage/exchange_access/publication_restrictions/publication_limitations">
		<uri_prefix>https://rdmo.nfdi4chem.de/terms</uri_prefix>
		<key>publication_limitations</key>
		<path>NFDI4Chem_Vorlage/exchange_access/publication_restrictions/publication_limitations</path>
		<dc:comment/>
		<attribute dc:uri="https://rdmorganiser.github.io/terms/domain/project/dataset/sharing/restrictions_explanation"/>
		<questionset dc:uri="https://rdmo.nfdi4chem.de/terms/questions/NFDI4Chem_Vorlage/exchange_access/publication_restrictions"/>
		<is_collection>True</is_collection>
		<is_optional>False</is_optional>
		<order>0</order>
		<help lang="en">Many researchers share their data at the end of a project. There are many reasons to
do that, such as to guarantee reproducibility and traceability of workflows and formats. Many
publishers also expect published data to accompany the text publication. For details, see
&lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1515/pac-2022-1001" target="_blank"&gt;The current landscape of author guidelines in chemistry through the lens of research data sharing&lt;/a&gt;.

However, there may be reasons against (direct) data publication. These may include the
commercial or industrial exploitation of data, or confidentiality related to security concerns.

In case that just the priority of a discovery needs to be protected, one possible solution is a
data publication with a so-called embargo or retention period, data publication is possible.
This requires the data to be already completely analysed and prepared, but allows to offer
them to the public audience at a later timepoint of your wish.

Further information can be found in the Code of Good Scientific Practice, namely within
Guideline 13 "&lt;a href="https://wissenschaftliche-integritaet.de/kodex/herstellung-von-offentlichem-zugang-zu-forschungsergebnissen/" target="_blank"&gt;Public Access to Research Results&lt;/a&gt;"</help>
		<text lang="en">Do you anticipate any implications or restrictions regarding subsequent publication or accessibility?</text>
		<default_text lang="en"/>
		<verbose_name lang="en"/>
		<verbose_name_plural lang="en"/>
		<help lang="de">Viele Forschende teilen die Daten am Ende eines Projektes. Dafür gibt es viele
Gründe wie beispielsweise die Reproduzierbarkeit und die Nachvollziehbarkeit der
Workflows und Formate. Auch immer mehr Verlage erwarten die publizierten Daten zu der
Textpublikation. Für Details siehe auch &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1515/pac-2022-1001" target="_blank"&gt;The current landscape of author guidelines in
chemistry through the lens of research data sharing&lt;/a&gt;.

Dennoch kann es Gründe geben, die gegen eine (direkte) Veröffentlichung der Daten
sprechen. Diese können beispielsweise die kommerzielle oder industrielle Verwertung der
Daten, oder Sicherheitsaspekte sein.
Eine mögliche Lösung in manchen Fällen, in denen lediglich die Präzedenz einer Entdeckung
geschützt werden soll, ist die Publikation der Daten mit einer sogenannten Sperr- oder
Embargofrist. Die setzt voraus, dass der Datensatz im Vorfeld schon fertig ausgewertet und
vorbereitet wird, stellt ihn aber erst zu einem erwünschten späteren Zeitpunkt der
Öffentlichkeit zur Verfügung.

Weitere Informationen können Sie aus dem Kodex zur Guten Wissenschaftlichen Praxis
entnehmen, und zwar aus der Leitlinie 13 "&lt;a href="https://wissenschaftliche-integritaet.de/kodex/herstellung-von-offentlichem-zugang-zu-forsch
ungsergebnissen/" target="_blank"&gt;Herstellung von öffentlichem Zugang zu
Forschungsergebnissen&lt;/a&gt;".</help>
		<text lang="de">Sind Auswirkungen oder Einschränkungen in Bezug auf die spätere Veröffentlichung bzw. Zugänglichkeit zu erwarten?</text>
		<default_text lang="de"/>
		<verbose_name lang="de"/>
		<verbose_name_plural lang="de"/>
		<default_option/>
		<default_external_id/>
		<widget_type>checkbox</widget_type>
		<value_type>option</value_type>
		<maximum/>
		<minimum/>
		<step/>
		<unit/>
		<width/>
		<optionsets>
			<optionset dc:uri="https://rdmo.nfdi4chem.de/terms/options/NFDI_publication-restrictions"/>
		</optionsets>
		<conditions/>
	</question>
	<section dc:uri="https://rdmo.nfdi4chem.de/terms/questions/NFDI4Chem_Vorlage/rights">
		<uri_prefix>https://rdmo.nfdi4chem.de/terms</uri_prefix>
		<key>rights</key>
		<path>NFDI4Chem_Vorlage/rights</path>
		<dc:comment/>
		<catalog dc:uri="https://rdmo.nfdi4chem.de/terms/questions/NFDI4Chem_Vorlage"/>
		<order>4</order>
		<title lang="en">Legal Obligations and Conditions</title>
		<title lang="de">Rechtliche Verpflichtungen und Rahmenbedingungen</title>
	</section>
	<questionset dc:uri="https://rdmo.nfdi4chem.de/terms/questions/NFDI4Chem_Vorlage/rights/legal_restrictions">
		<uri_prefix>https://rdmo.nfdi4chem.de/terms</uri_prefix>
		<key>legal_restrictions</key>
		<path>NFDI4Chem_Vorlage/rights/legal_restrictions</path>
		<dc:comment/>
		<attribute/>
		<section dc:uri="https://rdmo.nfdi4chem.de/terms/questions/NFDI4Chem_Vorlage/rights"/>
		<questionset/>
		<is_collection>False</is_collection>
		<order>0</order>
		<title lang="en">Legal Restrictions</title>
		<help lang="en"/>
		<verbose_name lang="en"/>
		<verbose_name_plural lang="en"/>
		<title lang="de">Rechtliche Einschränkungen</title>
		<help lang="de"/>
		<verbose_name lang="de"/>
		<verbose_name_plural lang="de"/>
		<conditions/>
	</questionset>
	<question dc:uri="https://rdmo.nfdi4chem.de/terms/questions/NFDI4Chem_Vorlage/rights/legal_restrictions/legal_aspects_2">
		<uri_prefix>https://rdmo.nfdi4chem.de/terms</uri_prefix>
		<key>legal_aspects_2</key>
		<path>NFDI4Chem_Vorlage/rights/legal_restrictions/legal_aspects_2</path>
		<dc:comment/>
		<attribute dc:uri="https://rdmorganiser.github.io/terms/domain/project/legal_aspects/ipr"/>
		<questionset dc:uri="https://rdmo.nfdi4chem.de/terms/questions/NFDI4Chem_Vorlage/rights/legal_restrictions"/>
		<is_collection>False</is_collection>
		<is_optional>False</is_optional>
		<order>0</order>
		<help lang="en">Legal aspects need to be considered when dealing with a dataset. Whether your data
are subject to copyright protection depends, among other things, on their originality. You can
find information on this in the "&lt;a href="https://www.rwth-aachen.de/global/show_document.asp?id=aaaaaaaaaavchxo" target="_blank"&gt;Copyright Protection of Research Data&lt;/a&gt;" factsheet or under
"Copyright and Licensing for Research Data" (https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5243232).
Answers to legal questions about Open Science can be found in the book "&lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.15460/HUP.211" target="_blank"&gt;Legal Issues in
Open Science&lt;/a&gt;" by Kreutzer and Lahmann.</help>
		<text lang="en">What is in place to consider aspects of use and copyright law as well as ownership issues?</text>
		<default_text lang="en"/>
		<verbose_name lang="en"/>
		<verbose_name_plural lang="en"/>
		<help lang="de">&lt;p&gt;Bei einem Datensatz gilt es die verschiedenen rechtlichen Aspekte zu berücksichtigen. Ob Ihre Daten dem urheberrechtlichen Schutz unterliegen, hängt unter anderem von der Schöpfungshöhe ab. Informationen hierzu finden Sie z.B. in dem &lt;i&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.rwth-aachen.de/global/show_document.asp?id=aaaaaaaaaavchxo" target="_blank"&gt;Merkblatt zum urheberrechtlichen Schutz von Forschungsdaten&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/i&gt; oder unter &lt;i&gt;&lt;a href="https://zenodo.org/record/5243232" target="_blank"&gt; Urheberrecht und Lizenzierung bei Forschungsdaten&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/i&gt;.&lt;br/&gt;
Antworten zu rechtlichen Fragen bei Open Science können Sie im Buch: &lt;i&gt;&lt;a href="https://hup.sub.uni-hamburg.de/oa-pub/catalog/book/205" target="_blank"&gt;„Rechtsfragen bei Open Science“&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/i&gt; von Kreutzer und Lahmann finden. 
&lt;/p&gt;</help>
		<text lang="de">Auf welche Weise werden nutzungs- und urheberrechtliche Aspekte sowie Eigentumsfragen berücksichtigt?</text>
		<default_text lang="de"/>
		<verbose_name lang="de"/>
		<verbose_name_plural lang="de"/>
		<default_option/>
		<default_external_id/>
		<widget_type>textarea</widget_type>
		<value_type>text</value_type>
		<maximum/>
		<minimum/>
		<step/>
		<unit/>
		<width/>
		<optionsets/>
		<conditions/>
	</question>
	<question dc:uri="https://rdmo.nfdi4chem.de/terms/questions/NFDI4Chem_Vorlage/rights/legal_restrictions/legal_aspects">
		<uri_prefix>https://rdmo.nfdi4chem.de/terms</uri_prefix>
		<key>legal_aspects</key>
		<path>NFDI4Chem_Vorlage/rights/legal_restrictions/legal_aspects</path>
		<dc:comment/>
		<attribute dc:uri="https://rdmorganiser.github.io/terms/domain/project/legal_aspects"/>
		<questionset dc:uri="https://rdmo.nfdi4chem.de/terms/questions/NFDI4Chem_Vorlage/rights/legal_restrictions"/>
		<is_collection>False</is_collection>
		<is_optional>False</is_optional>
		<order>1</order>
		<help lang="en">If you're going to handle personal data, please note it here. The handling of personal
data is regulated by the General Data Protection Regulation (GDPR). In addition, there are
data protection laws in various federal states. Please find out in advance. If you have any
questions about personal data and its security, please contact the data protection officer at
your university or research institution. Special conditions may arise from confidentiality
agreements with industrial collaborations or potential patenting. Briefly explain what these
special conditions entail.</help>
		<text lang="en">What are the legal specifics associated with the handling of research data in your project?</text>
		<default_text lang="en"/>
		<verbose_name lang="en"/>
		<verbose_name_plural lang="en"/>
		<help lang="de">Sollten Sie mit personenbezogenen Daten in Berührung kommen, sollten Sie
dieses hier vermerken. Der Umgang mit personenbezogenen Daten wird durch die
Datenschutzgrundverordnung (DSGVO) geregelt. Außerdem gibt es in den verschiedenen
Bundesländern Datenschutzgesetze. Informieren Sie sich bitte frühzeitig. Bei Fragen zu
personenbezogenen Daten und deren Sicherheit wenden Sie sich bitte an die
Datenschutzbeauftragten Ihrer Universität oder Forschungseinrichtung.
Treten die Besonderheiten durch Geheimhaltungserklärungen bei Industriekooperationen
oder durch eine mögliche Patentierung auf, erläutern Sie hier kurz, um was für
Besonderheiten es sich handelt.</help>
		<text lang="de">Welche rechtlichen Besonderheiten bestehen im Zusammenhang mit dem Umgang mit Forschungsdaten in Ihrem Projekt?</text>
		<default_text lang="de"/>
		<verbose_name lang="de"/>
		<verbose_name_plural lang="de"/>
		<default_option/>
		<default_external_id/>
		<widget_type>textarea</widget_type>
		<value_type>text</value_type>
		<maximum/>
		<minimum/>
		<step/>
		<unit/>
		<width/>
		<optionsets/>
		<conditions/>
	</question>
	<questionset dc:uri="https://rdmo.nfdi4chem.de/terms/questions/NFDI4Chem_Vorlage/rights/scientific_specifics">
		<uri_prefix>https://rdmo.nfdi4chem.de/terms</uri_prefix>
		<key>scientific_specifics</key>
		<path>NFDI4Chem_Vorlage/rights/scientific_specifics</path>
		<dc:comment/>
		<attribute/>
		<section dc:uri="https://rdmo.nfdi4chem.de/terms/questions/NFDI4Chem_Vorlage/rights"/>
		<questionset/>
		<is_collection>False</is_collection>
		<order>2</order>
		<title lang="en">Scientific Specifics</title>
		<help lang="en"/>
		<verbose_name lang="en"/>
		<verbose_name_plural lang="en"/>
		<title lang="de">Wissenschaftliche Besonderheiten</title>
		<help lang="de"/>
		<verbose_name lang="de"/>
		<verbose_name_plural lang="de"/>
		<conditions/>
	</questionset>
	<question dc:uri="https://rdmo.nfdi4chem.de/terms/questions/NFDI4Chem_Vorlage/rights/scientific_specifics/scientific_standards">
		<uri_prefix>https://rdmo.nfdi4chem.de/terms</uri_prefix>
		<key>scientific_standards</key>
		<path>NFDI4Chem_Vorlage/rights/scientific_specifics/scientific_standards</path>
		<dc:comment/>
		<attribute dc:uri="https://rdmorganiser.github.io/terms/domain/project/additional_rdm_policy/yesno"/>
		<questionset dc:uri="https://rdmo.nfdi4chem.de/terms/questions/NFDI4Chem_Vorlage/rights/scientific_specifics"/>
		<is_collection>True</is_collection>
		<is_optional>False</is_optional>
		<order>0</order>
		<help lang="en">In addition to general scientific codices, there are also chemistry-specific codices. If
you are not familiar with these, the &lt;a href="https://wissenschaftliche-integritaet.de/" target="_blank"&gt;DFG's page on scientific integrity&lt;/a&gt; can help. Here, you will find references to laws,
chemistry-specific commenting on guidelines and explanations, as well as case examples.</help>
		<text lang="en">Are there any significant research codes or professional standards to be taken into account?</text>
		<default_text lang="en"/>
		<verbose_name lang="en"/>
		<verbose_name_plural lang="en"/>
		<help lang="de">Neben allgemeinen wissenschaftlichen Kodizes gibt es auch chemie-spezifische
Kodizes. Falls Ihnen diese nicht bekannt sind, hilft Ihnen die Seite der DFG zur
&lt;a href="https://wissenschaftliche-integritaet.de/kommentare/links-rechtliche-ethische-rahmenbedingungen-nutzungsrechte/" target="_blank"&gt;wissenschaftlichen Integrität&lt;/a&gt; weiter. Hier finden Sie
Verweise auf Gesetze, chemiespezifische Kommentierungen der Leitlinien und
Erläuterungen sowie Fallbeispiele.</help>
		<text lang="de">Existieren wichtige wissenschaftliche Kodizes bzw. fachliche Normen, die Berücksichtigung finden sollten?</text>
		<default_text lang="de"/>
		<verbose_name lang="de"/>
		<verbose_name_plural lang="de"/>
		<default_option/>
		<default_external_id/>
		<widget_type>checkbox</widget_type>
		<value_type>option</value_type>
		<maximum/>
		<minimum/>
		<step/>
		<unit/>
		<width/>
		<optionsets>
			<optionset dc:uri="https://rdmo.nfdi4chem.de/terms/options/NFDI_scientific_guidelines"/>
		</optionsets>
		<conditions/>
	</question>
	<section dc:uri="https://rdmo.nfdi4chem.de/terms/questions/NFDI4Chem_Vorlage/responsibilities">
		<uri_prefix>https://rdmo.nfdi4chem.de/terms</uri_prefix>
		<key>responsibilities</key>
		<path>NFDI4Chem_Vorlage/responsibilities</path>
		<dc:comment/>
		<catalog dc:uri="https://rdmo.nfdi4chem.de/terms/questions/NFDI4Chem_Vorlage"/>
		<order>5</order>
		<title lang="en">Responsibilities and Resources</title>
		<title lang="de">Verantwortlichkeiten und Ressourcen</title>
	</section>
	<questionset dc:uri="https://rdmo.nfdi4chem.de/terms/questions/NFDI4Chem_Vorlage/responsibilities/responsibilities">
		<uri_prefix>https://rdmo.nfdi4chem.de/terms</uri_prefix>
		<key>responsibilities</key>
		<path>NFDI4Chem_Vorlage/responsibilities/responsibilities</path>
		<dc:comment/>
		<attribute/>
		<section dc:uri="https://rdmo.nfdi4chem.de/terms/questions/NFDI4Chem_Vorlage/responsibilities"/>
		<questionset/>
		<is_collection>False</is_collection>
		<order>0</order>
		<title lang="en">Responsibilities</title>
		<help lang="en"/>
		<verbose_name lang="en"/>
		<verbose_name_plural lang="en"/>
		<title lang="de">Verantwortlichkeiten</title>
		<help lang="de"/>
		<verbose_name lang="de"/>
		<verbose_name_plural lang="de"/>
		<conditions/>
	</questionset>
	<question dc:uri="https://rdmo.nfdi4chem.de/terms/questions/NFDI4Chem_Vorlage/responsibilities/responsibilities/datahandling_person">
		<uri_prefix>https://rdmo.nfdi4chem.de/terms</uri_prefix>
		<key>datahandling_person</key>
		<path>NFDI4Chem_Vorlage/responsibilities/responsibilities/datahandling_person</path>
		<dc:comment/>
		<attribute dc:uri="https://rdmorganiser.github.io/terms/domain/project/support"/>
		<questionset dc:uri="https://rdmo.nfdi4chem.de/terms/questions/NFDI4Chem_Vorlage/responsibilities/responsibilities"/>
		<is_collection>True</is_collection>
		<is_optional>False</is_optional>
		<order>0</order>
		<help lang="en">We recommend providing individuals in the following format: Title; First Name, Last
Name; ORCID (if available); Professional Position; Institute; Contact Information; Role in the
Project.</help>
		<text lang="en">Who is responsible for the appropriate handling of research data (description of roles and responsibilities within the project)?</text>
		<default_text lang="en"/>
		<verbose_name lang="en"/>
		<verbose_name_plural lang="en"/>
		<help lang="de">Wir empfehlen die Personen in folgender Form anzugeben: Titel; Vorname, Nachname; ORCID (falls vorhanden); berufl. Position; Institut; Kontaktdaten; Rolle im Projekt.</help>
		<text lang="de">Wer ist verantwortlich für den adäquaten Umgang mit den Forschungsdaten (Beschreibung der Rollen und Verantwortlichkeiten innerhalb des Projekts)?</text>
		<default_text lang="de"/>
		<verbose_name lang="de"/>
		<verbose_name_plural lang="de"/>
		<default_option/>
		<default_external_id/>
		<widget_type>text</widget_type>
		<value_type>text</value_type>
		<maximum/>
		<minimum/>
		<step/>
		<unit/>
		<width/>
		<optionsets/>
		<conditions/>
	</question>
	<question dc:uri="https://rdmo.nfdi4chem.de/terms/questions/NFDI4Chem_Vorlage/responsibilities/responsibilities/data_curate">
		<uri_prefix>https://rdmo.nfdi4chem.de/terms</uri_prefix>
		<key>data_curate</key>
		<path>NFDI4Chem_Vorlage/responsibilities/responsibilities/data_curate</path>
		<dc:comment/>
		<attribute dc:uri="https://rdmorganiser.github.io/terms/domain/project/dataset/pids/responsible_person/name"/>
		<questionset dc:uri="https://rdmo.nfdi4chem.de/terms/questions/NFDI4Chem_Vorlage/responsibilities/responsibilities"/>
		<is_collection>True</is_collection>
		<is_optional>False</is_optional>
		<order>1</order>
		<help lang="en">We recommend providing individuals in the following format: Title; First Name, Last
Name; ORCID (if available); Professional Position; Institute; Contact Information; Role in the
Project.</help>
		<text lang="en">Who is responsible for curating the data after the project's duration?</text>
		<default_text lang="en"/>
		<verbose_name lang="en"/>
		<verbose_name_plural lang="en"/>
		<help lang="de">Wir empfehlen die Personen in folgender Form anzugeben: Titel; Vorname, Nachname; ORCID (falls vorhanden); berufl. Position; Institut; Kontaktdaten; Rolle im Projekt.</help>
		<text lang="de">Wer ist nach Ende der Laufzeit des Projekts für das Kuratieren der Daten verantwortlich?</text>
		<default_text lang="de"/>
		<verbose_name lang="de"/>
		<verbose_name_plural lang="de"/>
		<default_option/>
		<default_external_id/>
		<widget_type>text</widget_type>
		<value_type>text</value_type>
		<maximum/>
		<minimum/>
		<step/>
		<unit/>
		<width/>
		<optionsets/>
		<conditions/>
	</question>
	<questionset dc:uri="https://rdmo.nfdi4chem.de/terms/questions/NFDI4Chem_Vorlage/responsibilities/resources">
		<uri_prefix>https://rdmo.nfdi4chem.de/terms</uri_prefix>
		<key>resources</key>
		<path>NFDI4Chem_Vorlage/responsibilities/resources</path>
		<dc:comment/>
		<attribute/>
		<section dc:uri="https://rdmo.nfdi4chem.de/terms/questions/NFDI4Chem_Vorlage/responsibilities"/>
		<questionset/>
		<is_collection>False</is_collection>
		<order>1</order>
		<title lang="en">Resources</title>
		<help lang="en"/>
		<verbose_name lang="en"/>
		<verbose_name_plural lang="en"/>
		<title lang="de">Ressourcen</title>
		<help lang="de"/>
		<verbose_name lang="de"/>
		<verbose_name_plural lang="de"/>
		<conditions/>
	</questionset>
	<question dc:uri="https://rdmo.nfdi4chem.de/terms/questions/NFDI4Chem_Vorlage/responsibilities/resources/datahandling_resources">
		<uri_prefix>https://rdmo.nfdi4chem.de/terms</uri_prefix>
		<key>datahandling_resources</key>
		<path>NFDI4Chem_Vorlage/responsibilities/resources/datahandling_resources</path>
		<dc:comment/>
		<attribute dc:uri="https://rdmorganiser.github.io/terms/domain/project/costs/usage/non_personnel"/>
		<questionset dc:uri="https://rdmo.nfdi4chem.de/terms/questions/NFDI4Chem_Vorlage/responsibilities/resources"/>
		<is_collection>True</is_collection>
		<is_optional>False</is_optional>
		<order>0</order>
		<help lang="en">This can include technical or IT resources as well as expertise, which may be provided
by data management or IT experts. You can provide more detailed information about each
item if necessary.</help>
		<text lang="en">What resources (costs, time, or other) are required to implement appropriate research data management in the project?</text>
		<default_text lang="en"/>
		<verbose_name lang="en"/>
		<verbose_name_plural lang="en"/>
		<help lang="de">Es kann sich hierbei sowohl um technische bzw. IT-Ressourcen handeln, als auch um Expertise, die z.B. durch Datenmanagement- oder IT-ExpertInnen eingebracht wird.&lt;br/&gt;
Machen Sie ggf. genauere Angaben zu den jeweiligen Posten.</help>
		<text lang="de">Welche Ressourcen (Kosten; Zeit oder anderes) sind erforderlich, um einen adäquaten Umgang mit Forschungsdaten im Projekt umzusetzen?</text>
		<default_text lang="de"/>
		<verbose_name lang="de"/>
		<verbose_name_plural lang="de"/>
		<default_option/>
		<default_external_id/>
		<widget_type>checkbox</widget_type>
		<value_type>option</value_type>
		<maximum/>
		<minimum/>
		<step/>
		<unit/>
		<width/>
		<optionsets>
			<optionset dc:uri="https://rdmo.nfdi4chem.de/terms/options/NFDI_resources"/>
		</optionsets>
		<conditions/>
	</question>
</rdmo>